A Guide to the Bigler-Sessler-John Family Papers, 1752-1924
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Bigler-Sessler-John Family Papers, 1752-1924
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1993-011
0.5 cu. ft. 1 box
The collection contains correspondence, legal documents, and accounting receipts and records relating to the Bigler, Sessler, and John families of southwest Virginia.
Bigler family; John family; Sessler family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was acquired by Special Collections in 1993.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, legal documents, and accounting receipts and records relating to the Bigler, Sessler, and John families who were connected to each other through marriage and resided predominantly in rural Southwest Virginia. The collection contains a varied array of documents including a math workbook from 1803, which belonged to Mark E. Sessler; a share cropping agreement between John Patterson and George Odewait from 1820; and a letter from Priscilla R. John to "Moll," which gives a very detailed description of revival and prayer meeting in Montgomery Co. in 1859. The documents in this collection provide insight into several facets of daily life in Southwest Virginia from the mid eighteenth century through the early twentieth century through the perspectives of members of the Bigler, Sessler, and John families.
Arrangement
Physical arrangement of the collection reflects the order in which the collection was received. The "Contents List" groups like materials together into series.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.); Slavery--United States
Geographical Names:
Virginia, Southwest
Contents List
- Correspondence and Invitations
  - Letter from Dora Lee to Mrs. Seesler, May 31, 1887 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Letter from P. Ruth to Naomi John, August 7, 1857 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Letter from Naomi John to Mary, March 1, 1860 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Letter from Priscilla R. John to Moll, August 24, 1859 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Letter from Sue to Naomi John, September 1863 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Free Franked by H. A. Edmundson Letter to Naomi John, March 2, 1865 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Letter from France to Cousin Mattie (Sessler), December 13, 1878 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Envelope addressed to Miss Mattie Sessler, October 22, from Texas (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Letter from France to Cousin Mattie (Sessler), February 12, 1878/79 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Letter from Wm. J. Walker (indenture) 1752 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Turned envelope addressed to Naomi John, March 22 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Letter to Mr. Biglor from John Gosogen, November 30, 1804 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Letter from George W. P. of Poplar Groce to Jo, January 22, 1857 (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Letter from George J. Etzler to J. B. Sesler, April 10, 1875 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - Letter from Dr. H. Black to Mr. James John, February 25, 1857 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - Letter from Eliza Hammon to Martha John, July 22, 1853 (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Letter from Naomi to Mrs. Elizabeth Sessler ("Lizzi"), October 27, 1889 (Box-folder 1-29)
  - Letter from Naomi to Mattie, January 8, 1890 (Box-folder 1-30)
  - Letter to Martha John from Sarah Henderson, August 10 (no year given) (Box-folder 1-31)
  - Letter to Mary Ann John from sister (no date) (Box-folder 1-32)
  - Letter to Lomie from Peter M. Deeds, May 30, 1875 (Box-folder 1-33)
  - Letter to Lomie (no date) (Box-folder 1-34)
  - Letter from Naomi Bishop to her sister Elizabeth Sessler, March 3 and 8, 1897 (Box-folder 1-35)
  - Letter from Naomi John Bishop to family, March 15, 1868 (Box-folder 1-36)
  - Letter from M. E. Gordin to family, April 18, 1882 (Box-folder 1-37)
  - Letter and cober from N. B. [Naomi Bishop] to Mrs. T. S. Henderson, December 31, 1876 (Box-folder 1-39)
  - 1 letter and 3 documents concerning case of David John, disabled son of deceased James and Anna John (Box-folder 1-40)
  - Letter from Martha to her sister Lizzie Sesler, February 15, 1883 (Box-folder 1-41)
  - Letter from Mark Sessler and his brother to Mattie, September 17, 1878 (Box-folder 1-42)
  - Letter from Naomi (John) Bishop to her father James John, November 1, 1875 (Box-folder 1-43)
  - Letter from M. E. Armstrong to Annie Gardner (Box-folder 1-46)
  - Letter from Penelope L. Holbrook to Naomi John, June 14, 1852 (Box-folder 1-47)
  - Letter from James John to his wife, March 6, 1858 (Box-folder 1-48)
  - Letter to Mattie Sesler, March 29, 1878 (Box-folder 1-49)
  - Miscellaneous folder #1 (Box-folder 1-55)
  - Letter from D. C. Allen to M. E. Sessler, Esq., February 23, 1893 (Box-folder 1-59)
  - Letter from Mattie Sessler to W. A. Watkins, May 10, 1882 (Box-folder 1-60)
  - Letter from Mattie [Sessler] to James B. Watkins, November 2, 1883 (Box-folder 1-61)
  - Letter from James L. Watkins (first page missing) (Box-folder 1-62)
  - Letter from James L. Watkins to his brother, September 19, 1906 (Box-folder 1-63)
  - Letter from James L. Watkins to Brother, July 8, 1906 (Box-folder 1-64)
  - Letter from J. B. Watkins to Mattie Sessler, March 19,1889 (Box-folder 1-65)
  - Letter from S. A. Watkins to brother, May 7, 1890 (Box-folder 1-66)
  - Letter from B. D. Painter to Mrs. J. B. Watkins, February 28, 1925 (Box-folder 1-67)
  - Wedding invitation to Mr. J. B. Watkins and family, Frances Marron Jamison to Marshall W. Mangus, October 18, 1910 (Box-folder 1-68)
  - Letter from Pearl watkins to mother Mrs. J. B. Watkins, October 13, 1902 (Box-folder 1-69)
  - Letter from Jane S. Dame Wood to unknown recipient, January 14, 1877 (Box-folder 1-70)
  - Letter from C. Byrd Manges to Mattie Sessler, December 17, 1878 (Box-folder 1-71)
  - Letter from Allice Walters to Cousin Anna Gardner, January 23, 1887 (Box-folder 1-72)
  - Letter from James B. Watkins to Mattie sessler, January 3, 1883 (Box-folder 1-73)
  - Letter from J. B. Watkins to Mattie Sessler, September 12, 1884 (Box-folder 1-74)
  - Letter from J. B. Watkins to Mattie Sessler, September 15, 1878 (Box-folder 1-75)
  - Letter to M. E. Sessler, October 18, 1893 (Box-folder 1-76)
  - Letter to Mattie from Uncle Harvey, June 12, 1882 (Box-folder 1-77)
  - Letter from J. H. H. Figgat to Mr. M. E. Sessler, October 18, 1891 (Box-folder 1-78)
  - Letter to "sister" from unknown author, no date (Box-folder 1-79)
  - Letter from Martha E. Brown to Emma and (reverse side) Naomi Bishop to Lizzie, February 10 and February 11, 1880 (Box-folder 1-80)
  - Letter from J. J. Bishop to Grandma, February 10, 1880 (Box-folder 1-81)
  - Letter from Priscilla [John] to her sister Tabitha S. Henderson, February 7, 1876 (Box-folder 1-82)
  - Letter to Mary Ann John from Sussanna McDonald (no date) (Box-folder 1-84)
  - Letter from M. A. Kirby to family (no date) (Box-folder 1-86)
  - Letter from M. W. Jones to Emma, June 5, 1888 (Box-folder 1-89)
  - Letter to James John from I. Frances, July 21, 1849 (Box-folder 1-21)
- Financial, Land, and Legal Documents
  - Share Cropping Agreement between John Patterson and George Odewait, February 27, 1820 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Account bill for Jacob Brunk to settle account of Jacob Garman, deceased, October 16, 1823 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - A list of hands for the road John Sessler, surveyor 1825 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Sesler Family births (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Note of payment of John Sesler, April 19, 1826 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Montgomery Co. Deed- Zacheriah Stanley to Henry Myers (Miers), April 4, 1797 (Box-folder 1-20)
  - Note of Payment from Morse Bigler to John Beckener c. October 1792 (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Claim of Jacob Bigler on Ambrose Myers, November 5, 1832 (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Indenture between Robert Watkins and Moses and William Watkins [Deed], June 14, 1851 (Box-folder 1-38)
  - Bill from R. H. Kyle and Co. to William John, John, and Son, Fincastle, August 21, 1829 (Box-folder 1-44)
  - Deed from John C. Gish to Mark B. Sessler, September 24, 1845 (Box-folder 1-45)
  - Notes and Receipts Folder #1 (Box-folder 1-50)
  - Notes and Receipts folder #2 (Box-folder 1-51)
  - Notes and Receipts Folder #3 (Box-folder 1-52)
  - Notes and Receipts Folder #4 (Box-folder 1-53)
  - Statement and Settlement of Accounts of M. E. Sessler, May 1900 (Box-folder 1-54)
  - Miscellaneous folder #2 (Box-folder 1-56)
  - Miscellaneous folder #3 (Box-folder 1-57)
  - Miscellaneous folder #4 (Box-folder 1-58)
  - List of accounts payable by James John to William A. Obenshain, October 21, 1846 (Box-folder 1-83)
  - Accounts payable by Jacob Bigler to John Layman, 1835-1844 (Box-folder 1-85)
  - Bill of Account of James John from J. R. C. Brown, October 26, 1844 (Box-folder 1-87)
  - Bill of Account to J. A. Bass, deceased from Moses Watkins, March-June 1861 (Box-folder 1-88)
  - Legal document to appoint Thos. W. Wrenne to represent Maggie G. Clark, February 13, 1895 (Box-folder 1-90)
- Notebooks and Ephemera
  - German Writing Exercise on Rag Paper (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Fancy Lettering Compliments of Sessler (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Math workbook of Mark E. Sesler, 1803, (Includes 1788 Fragment from an Architecture workbook) (Box-folder 1-26)